Guide to the CITYarts Inc. Records 1969-2016 MS 3096
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Project Binders, 1969-2016; 22 Linear feet in 22 cartons
  - Binder. Project 238: Why Should I Hide Me?, 2000 (Offsite-box 20)
    Mural, 230 West 146th Street.
  - Binder. Project 236: Cultural Mosaic, 2000 (Offsite-box 20)
    Mural, 210 West 146th Street. Includes program from unveiling. This project seems to be the same mural as the "Why Should I Hide Me?" mural listed separately in the master list as project 238.
  - Packet of Material for Cultural Mosaic Ribbon Cutting Ceremony, 2000 (Offsite-box 20)
    Includes program and speeches.
  - Binder. How to Make a Mural, 2000 (Offsite-box 20)
    This binder includes an educational guide to making public murals: "How to Make a Mural/An Educational Guide to Public Art" by CITYarts, as well as "Mural Manual" by Mark Rogovin and Marie Burton.
  - Binder. Project 244: Freedom to Imagine Mural (Whydam Makowsky Milestone Project), 2002 (Offsite-box 20)
    Also referred to as Wyn and His Friends Give Back (Bar Mitzvah Project). Includes correspondence, letter of agreement, and participant list. Also includes an unrelated booklet from Living on Mars (Project 230, 2000, Community Elementary School 64, 1425 Walton Avenue Bronx, with correspondence, press summary, sponsors list, article, and a certificate.
  - Binder. Project 245: Alice in Wall Street Land, 2002 (Offsite-box 20)
    Also referred to as Alice on the Wall. Mural, Stuyvesant School, Chambers Street and West Side Highway. Includes artist statement, article, correspondence, flyer, press release, sketches, etc.
  - Binder. Project 269: Doors of Hope (binder 1 of 2), 2008 (Offsite-box 20)
    Mural, New York to New Orleans. Eight City schools participated in the project as well as the Louisiana Children's Museum. In this binder are sketches, participant lists, photographs, and notes from each school.
  - Binder. Project 269: Doors of Hope (binder 2 of 2). Process Binder, 2008 (Offsite-box 20)
    Mural, New York to New Orleans. Eight City schools participated in the project as well as the Louisiana Children's Museum. In this binder are records concerning the process, contract, budget, legal forms, contact information, and supplemental materials. There are also some photographs and sketches from the schools involved. The photos and process files are both in paper and on two CDs.
  - Binder. Project 271: Grant's Tomb Mosaic Bench Restoration, 1972, 2008 (Offsite-box 21)
    2008 restoration of 1972 project (project 10). Includes fact sheet, correspondence, articles, and press releases.
  - Binder. Project 272: Nature is Love on Earth, 2009 (Offsite-box 21)
    Project within the program Engaging Graffiti Kids in Creation, not Destruction. St. John's Recreation Center, 1251 Prospect Place, Brooklyn. Includes flyers, poems, questionnaires, program, correspondence, press release, project schedule, and 4 CDs.
  - Binder. Project 277: Living Planters, 2009 (Offsite-box 21)
    Mural, Stonehenge Village, 120 West 97th Street. Includes flyers and fact sheet.
  - Binder. Project 285: Alice in Wall Street Land Restorations, 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 21)
    Restoration of 2010-11, Stuyvesant School, Chambers Street and West Side Highway. Includes proposal, artist statement, letter of permission, budget, participant waiver, media advisory, photos 2010-11, contacts 2011, and one CD.
  - Binder. Project 287: Pride, Respect, Peace, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 21)
    Mural, Polo Grounds Community Center. Includes proposal summary, proposal, executive summary, fundraising plan, budget, contacts, and 4 CDs.
  - Binder. Unidos Venceremos. Restoration re: Project 75, 1980, 2012 (Offsite-box 21)
    103rd Street between Lexington and Park Avenues. Includes schedule, assessment form, fact sheet, contact sheet, flyer, and artist bio. Although there are planning documents for a 2012 restoration, no documents here indicate the project was carried out. Most of the binder holds photographic slides of the original 1980 project.
  - Binder. Project 293: Celebrating the Heroes of Our City and Life Goes On, 2013 (Offsite-box 21)
    Mural, Henry M. Jackson Playground, intersection of Jackson, Madison, and Henry streets. Includes article, etc.
  - Binder A. Master Slide Binder, 1969-2002 (Offsite-box 21)
    Binder holds a selection of photographic slides from projects #1-237, though there are many gaps.
  - Binder B. Slides/Book No.2. 34th Street Commercial Bank, 1971 (Offsite-box 22)
    The binder holds a relatively small number of slides, most of which do not appear to be CITYarts projects, but examples of murals. There do appear to be a few slides here related to the "Black Women of America Today" project (1970, #5).
  - Binder C. Selected CITYarts Slides, 1972-1981 (Offsite-box 22)
    Binder holds various slides sleeved under the headings "Orientation, 1981," "Finished Shots" [of various projects], "Process Shots," "Detail Shots," "Festivals," "Copies," and 4 slides of Cityarts Workshop "old location" (2 exterior, 2 interior).
  - Binder D. Institutional Memory, 1979-1993 (Offsite-box 21)
    Binder holds a selection of news articles, brochures, publicity material, a few photos, and other documents providing an overview of the organization's first 25 years or so. A synopsis of each document in the binder is at the front.
  - Binder E. Creative Process Exhibit, 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 22)
    Project 155: Creative Process traveling exhibition, 1991, The Cork Gallery, Lincoln Center, Bronx Museum, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, and the Brooklyn Museum. Includes photographs and some planning documents.
  - Binder F. Various Pictures, 2003-2012 (Offsite-box 22)
    This binder holds thumbnail print-outs of digital photographs, including pictures from CITYarts Gala, Red Road To Mars, Berlin Peace Wall, UN Dinner, 44th Benefit, London Peace Wall, Discovery of Dreams, Milestone, etc. Overall, it appears that these are print-outs of at least some of the images from the CDs in the following binder (G).
  - Binder G. Random CDs, 2009-2012 (Offsite-box 22)
    Binder holds 63 CDs of benefits, ribbon-cuttings, and other events; projects (e.g., London and Berlin Peace Walls, Polo Grounds, Grant's Tomb bench 2008 restoration, various Pieces for Peace); CITYarts Powerpoint slideshow; overseas travel (Mexico, Jerusalem); etc. See binder F for what appear to be thumbnail print-outs of at least some of this digital content.
  - Binder H. Fact Sheets, 1971-1997 (Offsite-box 22)
    Binder holds fact sheets for projects from 1971-1997. These typically include basic information about a project and can often be found in the project-specific binders above.
  - Binder I. Project Cards, 1974-2007 (Offsite-box 22)
    Binder holds samples of postcards produced by CITYarts with images of projects.
- Series II. Pieces for Peace Project, 2004-2016; 8 Linear feet in 8 cartons + part of an oversize box
  The series includes some administrative files concerning arrangements for the various aspects of the Pieces for Peace project, including solicitation of school/children participants, traveling exhibition of samples, and mosaic Peace Walls in various locations; photographs of the artworks and related events; and Pieces for Peace original artwork submissions (drawings on paper) from around the world.
  The series is arranged by document type/format.
  - Project administration files, 2005-2010 (Offsite-box 23)
    Includes files on general administration of the project and some country specific files. Includes some files on the iEARN conferences in Egypt and Uzbekistan.
  - Project administration files, 2007-2011 (Offsite-box 24)
    Includes a set of country-specific files in alphabetical sequence concerning potential and actual participants in the program, and a set of files related to the project's Peace Wall in Israel (2010-11).
  - Project administration binders, 2005-2016 (Offsite-box 25)
    Box holds 6 binders related to the Pieces for Peace traveling exhibition (contact lists, press information, sponsors, fliers/publicity, budgets/expenses, venue lists, thumbnail photos of some exhibitions, copies and some originals of letters of support (original signed letter from Israel President Shimon Peres); and 2 binders related to the international Peace Walls in Karachi, Pakistan and, especially, Tel Aviv, Israel.
  - Project photograph binders, 2004-2008 (Offsite-box 26)
    Includes 4 binders: New York City Peace Wall in Jacob H. Schiff Park in Harlem, 2004-05 (CDs of photos with print-outs of thumbnails, some snapshots, publicity); thumbnails of photos of works used in the traveling exhibition and images originally submitted by various countries (with some CDs of images and some background information); DVDs of London Project (no thumbnails/prints); and photographs of the Pieces for Peace exhibition and opening reception at the Gabarron Foundation-Carriage House Center for the Arts in New York (2007).
  - Artwork, circa 2009-2010s (Offsite-box 27)
    Original Pieces for Peace drawings from children, filed in alphabetical sequence by country. This box holds countries Belarus to Iraq.
  - Artwork, circa 2009-2010s (Offsite-box 28)
    Original Pieces for Peace drawings from children, filed in alphabetical sequence by country. This box holds countries Mexico to the United Kingdom. United States then starts, foldered by specific school/location.
  - Artwork, circa 2009-2010s (Offsite-box 29)
    Original Pieces for Peace drawings from children, filed in alphabetical sequence by country. This box continues from above with the United States, foldered by specific school/location.
  - Artwork, circa 2009-2010s (Offsite-box 30)
    Original Pieces for Peace drawings from children, filed in alphabetical sequence by country. This box continues from above with the remaining United States submissions, foldered by specific school/location. The sequence then concludes with folders of artwork for the exhibition at the United Nations, 2010. The box then includes a few "out of order" country artwork folders: France, Ghana, Israel, and Campion School in London.
  - Artwork (oversize flat box), undated (Offsite-box 58)
    Includes oversize artwork from P.S. 328 and various textured collages with glitter
- Series III. General Program Administration Files, 1970s-2016; 13 Linear feet in 13 cartons + 1 flat file folder
  The series includes records related to the general administration of the organization and its programs. These files primarily concern fundraising through annual benefit events and sponsorships of particular projects, and publicity and media coverage of CITYarts and its work. Some files concern administrative matters for particular projects, reference files dating from the 1970s about urban murals generally, financial data, and some Board level documents. The container list provides further detail of the content for each box.
  The series is arranged roughly by subject matter.
  - Benefit binders, 1993-1998 (Offsite-box 31)
    Primarily photographs of the events, with some publicity materials and sponsor/financial-related information.
  - Benefit binders, 1999-2002 (Offsite-box 32)
    Includes primarily photographs of the events with publicity and related documents.
  - Benefit binders, 2003-2006 (Offsite-box 33)
    Primarily photos with some "process" and publicity
  - Benefit binders, 2007-2010 (Offsite-box 34)
  - Designing Brick Awards, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 34)
    Photographs of the annual award, identifying the artist and honoree.
  - Anniversary benefit programs, 2007-2016 (Offsite-box 44)
    Includes the program, invitations, and related documents from the award/benefit events from the 40th anniversary (2008) to the 48th (2016). Also includes the DVD for the 39th anniversary (2007) and a general CITYarts publicity DVD.
  - Press clippings (binders), 1977-2010 (Offsite-box 35)
    4 binders of clippings and other publicity materials, 1977-2010.
  - Publicity binders; publicity kits, 1978-2016 (Offsite-box 36)
    Binder of press releases and event fliers, 1978-2002; binder of "Constant Contact" press updates, 2003-2009; binder of photocopies of letters of support from politicians, government officials, etc., 1983-2016, with packet of thank you letters from children, 2015; binder of publicity brochures, especially for awards and benefits; and six packets of publicity material, including for Pieces for Peace and related book, 1984-circa 2010.
  - Publicity files, 1977-1986 (Offsite-box 37)
    Folders of clippings and other press coverage of specific CITYarts projects or general coverage. Also includes a small set of files with results from a 1980 survey concerning public reactions to certain murals.
  - Publicity files; Loose publicity cards, etc., 1987-2000s (Offsite-box 38)
    The box holds the continuation of publicity files from 1987-1999. It also holds packets of miscellaneous postcards and other publicity pieces from the 1990s-2000s found loose in the collection.
  - Publicity files, 2000-2010 (Offsite-box 39)
    Folders of clippings and other press coverage of specific CITYarts projects or general coverage.
  - Subject reference files, 1970s (Offsite-box 40)
    Includes extensive files on various arts, community arts projects, especially murals, and organizations across the United States, including Baltimore, Chicago, Haight-Ashbury, and many others. These files do not appear to concern specific CITYarts projects, but seem more for reference about community murals generally.
  - General project files, 1972-2000s (Offsite-box 41)
    Includes a broad mix of files that generally appear to concern potential CITYarts projects (or project concepts), sponsors, funding, partnerships, and the like. Some files date to the 1970s; one of these is a field studies assessment of CITYarts done by Heriverto Alicea in 1976 in connection with his coursework for a fundraising workshop held by the Community Service Society.
  - General project files, 2008-2012 (Offsite-box 42)
    Includes administrative files on various projects, including, among others Harlem RBI, Grant's Tomb Bench Restoration, Celebrating Our Heroes, Polo Grounds, and Alice in Wall Street Land Restoration.
  - General project files, 1970s-2000s (Offsite-box 43)
    Includes some publicity and press releases from the 1970s; newsletters, operating proposals, mural lists and other general files from the 1980s; volunteers information and forms, potential sites and partnerships, and other general information for 1990s-2000s.
  - "State of murals in Manhattan", 1998 (Offsite-box 44)
    Binder of photographs and brief descriptive assessments conducted in 1998 of the condition of murals sponsored by CITYarts in prior years.
  - Board meeting documents, 2001, 2005-2009 (Offsite-box 44)
  - Financial data (binder), 2001-2016 (Offsite-box 44)
  - Floor plans by architect Gene Kaufman for the CITYarts' offices at 525 Broadway (oversize flat file), 2011 (Folder FF-1)
- Series IV. Audiovisual (RESTRICTED), 1974-2009; 8 Linear feet in 8 cartons
  The series primarily includes about 207 videocassettes, primarily from the 1990s into the very early 2000s, with some earlier and later. Most of these are labeled and dated. Generally, the content includes benefits, opening events, publicity pieces, clips from news reports and other television segments about CITYarts or particular projects (some are from overseas media), program activities, celebrity visits, interviews, and the like.
  The videocassettes are in multiple formats, including both VHS and Betamax, as well as others. Many of the videos have multiple versions (e.g., master, edited, etc.). Most of the videocassettes are ordered with an alphabetical sequence code, which is roughly chronological. For example, the video beginning the sequence with "A" is "Community Murals" from 1978 and the latest in the sequence is "TTT" from an event in 2007. The code also serves in most cases to link related cassettes together; for example, all 12 cassettes with code "AA" relate to the "A dream grows in Red Hook" project.
  The series also holds a small number of other formats, specifically film reels (including CITYarts' educational film "How to do a mural"), a videotape, and an audiotape.
  Most of the series is arranged following the alphabetical sequence coding given the videocassettes by CITYarts, which is roughly chronological. Cassettes without a sequence code, and other formats, are at the end of the series. This arrangement is modified at points to account for storage needs of media of different sizes.
  - Videocassettes, 1986-1994 (Offsite-box 45)
    Includes 31 tapes coded E-Y (some gaps). Tapes include, among several others, those that relate to "Making a difference through the arts"; overseas TV coverage of "The nature of this flower is to bloom," including opening with Alice Walker; and pool mural at Fort Hamilton High School.
  - Videocassettes, 1994-1997 (Offsite-box 46)
    Includes 33 tapes coded AA, BB, LL, MM, and one not coded. Among several other topics, these concern "A dream grows in Red Hook" and "Young minds build bridges." About 10 tapes appear to have been coded BB retroactively to fit a chronological sequence, but relate to various benefits, public service announcements, etc.
  - Videocassettes, 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 47)
    Includes 34 tapes coded CC, OO, QQ, RR, TT, UU, and one not coded. Among several other topics, these concern "Young minds build bridges" and "Kids for justice."
  - Videocassettes, 1998-2001 (Offsite-box 48)
    Includes 31 tapes coded SS-ZZ (with gaps) and AAA-EEE. Among several other topics, these concern"Kids for peace"; "Kids for justice"; "Living on Mars"; and "Forever Tall."
  - Videocassettes; Film reel, 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 49)
    Includes 32 tapes coded FFF-TTT, with gaps, and several not coded. Among several other topics, these concern "Celebrating the heroes of our city"; "Alice on Wall Street"; a "Pieces for peace" exhibition; and several benefits. Also one unidentified reel of film.
  - Videocassettes; Videotape; Audiotape; Film reels, 1974, 2002 (Offsite-box 50)
    Includes 22 tapes, mostly from 2002, including "Alice on Wall Street" and "Celebrating the heroes of our city"; several are unidentified. Also, a videotape of "Community Murals" by Eva Cockcroft and Daniel del Solar; a reel-to-reel audiotape (of guitar music by Heitor Villa-Lobos?), 1974; and 3 film reels in box labeled "How to do a mural."
  - Videocassettes (oversize cartridges); Film reel, 1978-1997 (Offsite-box 51)
    Includes 12 tapes with oversize cartridges. Includes codes A,C,D,N,R,X, and CC. Among other topics includes "Young minds build bridges" and "Community murals." Also includes 1 film reel titled "Great Wall of LA."
  - Videocassettes (oversize cartridges), 1982-2005 (Offsite-box 52)
    Includes 12 tapes in oversize cartridges. Includes codes B (a tape from Fuji TV "Story on Avenue C") and CC ("Young minds build bridges"). Other uncoded tapes relate to benefits or are not well identified.
- Series V. Artwork, Miscellaneous Photographs, and Other Visual Materials, 1970s-2011; 11.5 Linear feet in 8 boxes of various size + 4 flat file folders
  The series is composed of various visual materials found more or less as standalone items in the collection (that is, not found within particular contexts such as the project binders or program files). The material primarily includes artworks, photographs, reproductions of photographs on boards for display, and posters.
  Artworks include drawings in crayon, pencil/color pencil, pen and ink, and watercolors. They generally depict murals or details of murals. Most are uncaptioned and undated, so it is not certain if these were proposals or as executed.
  Photographs include slides, color and black-and-white prints, and oversize prints and reproductions. These depict completed murals, the process of creating the murals, and various events.
  The series is arranged roughly by format and size of materials.
  - Photographic slides, 1968-1990s (Offsite-box 53)
    This box holds a small container of slides from the late 1960s and possibly early 1970s, and 3 carousels of slides: 2 noted as "How to make [or do] a mural" and one noting it includes highlights compiled in 1994.
  - Photographic slides, 1970s? (Offsite-box 54)
    This box holds three carousels of slides. Produced by Cityarts Workshop, they appear to be educational tools. Titles of the compilations are: "The Mexican mural renaissance: Part 1: Mexican history," "The Mexican mural renaissance: Los Tres Grandes: Diego Rivera, Jose Clemente & David Alfaro," and "New Deal: WPA."
  - Black-and-white photographs, 1970s-1992 (Offsite-box 55)
    This box holds unsorted b&w 8x11 inch photographs of murals and the process of creating murals. Most are undated and uncaptioned, but those that are identified date primarily from the 1970s, with some into the 1980s and 1990s. There are many duplicates and the photos have warped, though the image remains clear. There are some negatives and contact sheets.
  - Photographs, undated (Offsite-box 56)
    This box holds various photographs of murals, the process of creating murals, and benefits and other events. Few are captioned or dated, but range into the 2000s. The photos are both assorted and those that were compiled as an album, or mounted on boards, or formed as a set in some other way. Most of the photographs are color prints, but some are black-and-white, negatives, or on digital discs.
  - Artwork; Photographs; Printed Material (oversize flat box), 1980s-2011 (Offsite-box 57)
    This oversize flat box includes:
    Photograph album from the 5th annual "Arts Are Cooking" Benefit Buffet
    Artworks including, among others:
    *Pen and ink drawings seemingly of African-American, Hispanic, and labor history.
    * Watercolors from students in Germany, 2005
    * Crayon drawings on Global Warming theme, 2007
    Oversize photographs of murals and other installations.
    Printed material, including:
    * 2 CITYarts posters (Peace Night, 41st anniversary)
    * Poster for Bravo's Arts for Change campaign
    * 2 certificates of accomplishment in connection with the Peace Wall in Tel Aviv, 2011
    * Mock-ups
  - Artwork (oversize flat box), 2007, undated (Offsite-box 58)
    1 oil painting on wood; 2 oils on canvas
  - Photographs; Printed Material (oversize flat box), 1970s-2007 (Offsite-box 59)
    This oversize (36x24 inch) flat box includes:
    * poster on board, with photograph, for the opening of Broadway Starship "play sculpture" in Corporal Thompson Park, West Brighton, Staten Island, 1985, and 4 design drawings by Gillian Bradshaw-Shaw for Broadway Starship, 1984
    * news clippings/publicity glued to board, 1970s
    * 14 images (matted photographs or photoreproductions on foamcore) of murals, creating murals, or events, including Kids for Justice event with Susan Sarandon
    * 4 CITYarts posters (Pieces for Peace, Forever Tall, 41st anniversary event, and 40th anniversary event, which is mounted on aluminum)
    * mock-up for a brochure for tours of CITYarts projects, 2007.
  - Artwork (oversize flat box), 1970s-2000s (Box 61)
    Includes:
    * 5 matted drawings on the theme of peace
    * 2 color drawings (pencil?) of proposals inviting comment for a "Women's mural" on the Garden Cafeteria at East Broadway and Essex Street, 1970s?
    * 4 color pencil drawings for a Chinatown mural, 1977
    * color pencil drawing by J. Stephenson of an Avenue D mural
    * blueline drawings of design by Lucinda Luvass of the left and right walls for the Louis Armstrong mural, 1981,and a crayon drawing of the right wall (see also flat files below for additional Armstrong drawings)
    * Drawings for "Forever Tall" [World Trade Center, 2001]
    * "Creative Process" exhibition poster, hand-colored, 1990
    * various other drawings.